so
wow
uh
[Music]
hello everyone i hope you are doing very
well
welcome to the 57th live episode of the
ask abhijit show
and as you know today we go back to the
old format i am going to answer
questions from the comments that you
have
submitted
so i ran this poll recently as you as
most of you would know and many of you
have voted on it and the results are
very clear i had asked about which is
the format that you prefer the most
whether it's questions taken from
comments questions taken from live chat
or questions taken from
face-to-face video chat and
almost three-fourths of you have said
that the questions taken from comments
that format is the best that offers you
the most value
so going forward i'm gonna go mostly
back to that format tomorrow i'm gonna
have a live chat
session not live video chat but just
live chat
but next week onwards i think i'm gonna
go back mostly to this format taking
questions from comments and answering
those questions
so that's what i'm going to do today i
have selected a number of comments
number of questions that i've taken from
the comments and i'm going to answer
these
starting right now
so let's get right into the first
question the first question is by anmol
the question is can a student with
non-science background learn c plus plus
or java and the answer is very simple
the answer is yes anybody can learn c
plus plus java python any programming
language programming languages are at
their very core very simple they're all
based on simple logic
and you learn the basics and you build
upon that
and it's something that if you learn
systematically step by step starting
from the very beginning then anybody can
learn even a 12 year old 13 year old kid
can learn c
java python c any of these programming
languages
so yes you don't need a science
background for this you don't need a
mathematics or any kind of background
you can go straight into this without
any
prerequisite understanding or knowledge
of anything right so i hope that answers
the question
let's go to the second question
okay this is by dungar singh johan the
question is can we rely on accounts of
chinese pilgrims like schwanzong or
fahyan
is everything mentioned by them true
because we know records of
foreign travelers help us
to know about our history
uh
that's a good question because of late
we have seen that uh
the accounts of europeans
and turks have been extremely like
they are quite distorted they portray a
very
distorted and biased uh
perspective or account of india and its
culture and in its history
now when it comes to the accounts of
chinese pilgrims chinese travelers like
shwanzang fahyan
etc it's a very different story
these uh
pilgrims who came to india came to india
in search of knowledge in search of
wisdom
uh the chinese regarded india as the
abode of heaven i think the the term
they used was
kyansha or something like that which
means the center of heaven
and they
greatly valued india's knowledge india's
wisdom india's scriptures
and they wished to study these
scriptures in detail to understand
to study and understand india's society
and culture in detail and imbibe the
best of that and take it back to china
and incorporate that into chinese
culture and civilization and that's what
they did
so pilgrims like schwanzong and fahiyan
they came to india they wrote extensive
accounts of the travels of what they saw
in india
of the kind of lifestyle the indians had
the kind of knowledge we had the kind of
universities we had the education system
they learned sanskrit in order to
communicate with us indians and so on
and i would say that those accounts that
they wrote
were actually quite faithful to the
truth
and uh
one can trust those accounts because
there was no hidden agenda behind those
accounts behind what they wrote
so i think we can certainly trust the
accounts of the ancient chinese
travelers so yes because see
the thing is that we have lost most of
our written history all of it was
destroyed in the destruction of our
great universities and the burning of
the great libraries
so what little is left is the accounts
of many foreigners we find lots of
accounts that were
written by chinese pilgrims by tibetans
by central asians uh there is the
the cave of the thousand buddhas which
oral stein
excavated and he took everything all the
texts away from center from from
northern tibet
western china into england i think most
of those texts are now housed in
the british museum or something like
that
and in a way it was good that this
happened because the chinese communist
party went ahead and destroyed all these
ancient texts whatever they could find
so in a way this saved and preserved
those ancient texts so i think that
whatever the chinese wrote about india
in those days it was quite faithful it
was quite accurate and it certainly will
if we study that
it will certainly help us understand our
past better
so to answer in short yes we can
certainly rely on those accounts of the
chinese in ancient times
avinash kali asks what would happen if
mars was our moon in its current orbit
that's an interesting thought experiment
so the question is
instead of the moon what if suddenly the
ma the planet mars was there in the same
orbit around earth not further away but
in the same orbit around the earth
so that's an interesting thought
experiment let's talk about what happens
to what would happen to mars first see
mars is all the way further out
away from the sun or and it's further
out from the sun as compared to earth
and that's why it is so cold because
uh the distance to the sun is much
greater now if mars were to come into
earth's orbit where the moon is
currently
then it would get
essentially the same amount of sunlight
as the earth gets today and therefore
its atmosphere would heat up
significantly i think the average
temperature on mars on the surface of
mars is somewhere around
minus 30 minus 40 minus 50 degrees
celsius something like that
approximately
so if it were to come into earth's orbit
the
average temperature
would rise significantly its average
temperature could possibly be around 20
25 degrees
celsius
and this would have significant effects
on the
atmosphere of mass mars because all the
frozen carbon dioxide which is currently
frozen in in the form of dry ice
on and under masses uh soil would
evaporate it would create a thicker
atmosphere all the water that is frozen
there would also even would also melt
some of it would evaporate so we would
quickly see
a resurgence in the atmosphere of mars
so the atmosphere would get thicker
maybe the atmospheric pressure would
could probably increase greatly
it may even be possible for human beings
to walk around without any suits of any
kind possibly
and so yeah the the
conditions on mars would mars would
change significantly they would become
very much more earth-like than they are
right now now what is the effect on
earth
so the moon is a very small uh
object
its mass
is i think
one-sixth of that of earth i think the
mars
mass is at least i'm not sure what
exactly it is it's significantly more
than that of the moon at least twice
there of the moon and therefore the
tidal pull that this planet would effect
would exert on our planet would be
significant
so today because of the uh
presence of the moon you have these
tides in the in the ocean
on earth
now if mars was there those tides would
be significantly larger
they could be tsunami-sized tides you
know
and you could get you would see
significant flooding of the coastal
areas of the earth twice a day
and the
gravitational pull of the planet would
also cause significant
tectonic activity on the earth you would
see an upsurge in volcanism you would
see an upsurge in earthquakes and things
like that
so it could significantly uh change the
entire uh
the entire
climate and everything on earth yeah
and even the tectonic activity and
right now what happens is that during
night time if the full moon is there you
get a little bit of light
uh that shines down upon you if the mars
were if mars was there you would see a
significantly more a significantly
greater output of light which would be
reflected sunlight and therefore the
night sky would change significantly it
would get much brighter people's
circadian cycles would circadian cycles
would change the circadian cycles of
animals and birds and insects etc would
change so it could have a significantly
disruptive effect
on
life as it exists on earth you could
have mass extinctions
and many other things which you can't
even
many of the second or third order fourth
order effects that you can't even
predict
uh accurately
so that's the kind of thing that would
happen if mars was
our moon
would replace
our moon in the current orbit it's an
interesting thought experiment but of
course that's never going to happen
but interesting question nice to see
this okay next question
this is by survey some historians argue
that the executions of guru arjun and
guru take bahadur
as well as the executions of the two
young sons of guru govind singh were
purely political moves what are my
thoughts
yes so if you ask india's court
historians the the
establishment historians the so-called
darbari historians
the rumila toppers the irfan habibs and
so on and so forth they would tell you
that these were merely political moves
there was no other motive
in doing this
uh the
the turkic emperors turkic kings were
simply doing this for the sake of
political experiences to get rid of
certain political opponents
uh these uh
these gurus
were
political opponents of the turkic kings
and nothing more that's what they would
say
now the truth is is much is quite
different from that
uh sikhism emerged as
a form of resistance to the turkic
occupation of india
so uh
in northern india in the punjab
etc region
this new resistance came up
it was hindus who decided to dedicate
their lives
to freeing the homeland the motherland
from the turkic invaders and occupiers
and oppressors and they decided to live
a certain lifestyle a very
hard
martial lifestyle they would not cut
their hair they would wear turbans they
would not shave off their beards they
would always carry a weapon on them so
this was a militaristic lifestyle it's
the entire they dedicated their entire
existence
to eradicating
the presence of the occupiers the turks
from the motherland from india
so this was a cultural resistance it was
a military resistance it was also
religious resistance and the original
sikhs were very clear that there were
hindus
guru
nanak et cetera they were very clear
that they were defending protecting
hinduism maharaja ranjit singh also had
goddess durga i think on his flag and he
forbade cow slaughter and all that so it
is it was very clear until the time that
sikhs were
they were
there were militaristic hindus it was
simply a lifestyle that they had adopted
in order to free india from the foreign
occupier so this was a great challenge
to the turks because the turkic project
was to wipe out india's indigenous
culture traditions religion architecture
everything and convert everybody to that
foreign religion that was very that was
their
overall
big picture objective right
and these gurus
they they presented a very
formidable challenge
and obstacle in the path of this
objective of converting all india to the
foreign religion and to wipe out india's
culture because this sort of resistance
is something they did not expect
and therefore the execution of guru
arjun by
what's his name salim right the turkic
uh
invader king saleem
who is popularly known in textbooks as
jahangir
so jahangir saleem ordered the execution
of guru arjun as a means of
of cowing down
the people of india the hindus
and telling that the sea this is what we
did to your leader
so don't resist resistance it's futile
that was the message that was sent that
was supposed to be sent out it is not a
political thing it's a cultural thing
the objective was to wipe out india's
culture and similarly when it comes to
guru tegh bahadur it he was beheaded
on the order of the tyrant
muhammad uh
popularly known in textbooks as
aurangzeb
aurangzeb was one of the most brutal
barbarians who ever ruled upon india
and
again he's he was a very very staunch
and uh fundamentalist person
and his uh his life's uh objective was
very clear to wipe out hinduism and all
traces of indian culture from india
and the objective in in uh having guru
take bahadur executed was to
send a message to all hindus to all
indians in
six
that your resistance is not going to
succeed
so it was not
a political thing it was
essentially an act of terrorism
it was an act of terror that's what it
was
and the
message was cultural it was that your
religion your culture is inferior to us
because see this is what we have we were
able to do it to your gurus
and similarly aurangzeb again did this
to the two young sons of guru gobind
singh he had them bricked alive into a
wall
two young boys
so these are the kind of barbarians
brutes
inhuman beasts who rule india and it is
a travesty that we some of us still
wish to
whitewash their
brutal barbaric inhuman
crimes against humanity
so these were not political moves these
were
acts of terror of religious and cultural
terror nothing short of that
okay next question
this is by akash welcome back akash
so the question is that it's generally
accepted that humans started settling
around rivers and shifted to agriculture
from hunting and gathering food
around 10 000 bce
my question is how do these researchers
and archaeologists know that this is the
case for the entire earth it's rather
odd that all the humans developed
cutting tools etc got the knowledge of
crops all together independently
throughout the entire world at the same
time 10 000 bce
i personally feel that a marvelous and
complex civilization like ours could be
much older than these findings what was
possibly going on in bharat
at that time and how sure are we that
the currently accepted theory of
evolution of humans in the neolithic
period is accurate this is an excellent
question so the consensus view is that
we moved on from hunting gathering and
and became pastoral agriculturists
around 10 000 bce and this happened
apparently in the so-called cradle of
civilization which is the middle east
mesopotamia that region right so this is
the consensus
of consensus view of all mainstream
historians etc
now what evidence do we have for that
very little evidence
if you look on in only one place you
will find only evidence from that place
and then you will portray that as the
uh
if you if you then go on and portray
that as something that is
applicable to the entire world it is the
height of idiocy and stupidity
right so that's the way history has been
done thus far
i mean uh
even with the very little archaeology
that's been done in india we know that
india civilization is around nine and a
half ten thousand years old we have
explored less than one percent of the
archaeological sites that are available
in this country when it comes to
the uh
the so-called
fertile crescent and when it comes to
egypt there are hundreds of
archaeologists working in these two
regions every year year after year after
year there is detailed meticulous
research
and archaeological work being done every
year in these places
and that's on it's in it's on the basis
of all that that they have come up with
these claims
now imagine if we would if we were to do
the same kind of detailed methodological
methodical
uh archaeological work in india with
hundreds of archaeologists year after
year after year for 20 years imagine the
depths
of new information the wealth of new
information we would be able to uncover
so that is the
problem our historians our
archaeologists refuse
to
to do archaeological work in india and
that's why we are not able to find the
truth about india
we know that india's civilization is
very old much much older than 10 000 bce
genetics tells a very
very striking story that india's
the indian origin r1
haplogroup is about 17 to 26 000 years
old at least right and the oldest
non-african haplogroup in the world
which is which accounts for more than 90
percent of males
outside of africa non-african males
that is the haplogroup f which is about
65 70 000 years old which originated in
india and similarly for matrilineal
groups so india's population is the
world's oldest non-african population it
is the place from which all other
non-african populations
uh emerged it is the original founder
zone and therefore if we were to do
archaeological work in detail in depth
in all parts of india we would find a
story that would astound the world i
think that indians would have
moved away from hunting gathering way
before 1000 bce because india is such a
fertile subcontinent
the climatic conditions are so
uh hospitable to human habitation there
is no frost there are no droughts it's
very it's a very uh fertile soil
very good monsoon very lush uh
very lush forest and all that
and i and therefore it's it's
incomprehensible that we are not looking
deeper into this i think human
civilization emerged in india it must
have been way before 10 000 bce we
already know that uh the oldest evidence
of the cultivation of rice
is from india it is as old as the
evidence that has been found in china
and we have looked at less than one
percent of the archaeological sites we
also know that the
serie culture the cultivation of the
silkworm
is also equal just as old in india as it
is in china maybe it actually may have
emerged from india
and so on and so forth so with with the
very little work and data that we have
we already have been able to establish
an incredible amount of antiquity of our
civilization so we just need to
invest our government needs to invest in
in studying our history in greater depth
so it's clear that this story is utter
nonsense this 10 000 bc store
story and even if you look at the work
of people like graham hancock for
instance it's very clear that
there is clear evidence of
very ancient human civilizations in
other parts of the world like in
the americas in southern america in
northern america the the two continents
and so on
so it's clear that the human story is
much older and much more complex than
what we have been led to believe what
the consensus of all these eminent
historians and archaeologists is all
these stories are going to be washed out
in the next 20 years or so as science
throws up new evidence thus far
history and archaeology has been the
domain of historians and archaeologists
now the problem for these great
individuals is that scientists
are getting into this research
and science is going to upend all the
information all the dogma that these
people have created so it's just a
matter of time but it's a very good
question and i think that uh
like you said that the currently
accepted theories of all these theories
are highly inaccurate and the entire
story is going to change in short order
very interesting
question and observations
okay this is by
kondinia
and the question is that china became
the first country to test hypersonic
missiles and are meanwhile planning to
annex taiwan can the united states or
any other superpower do anything to stop
china annexing taiwan
all right so first of all there's only
one superpower in the world which is the
united states
the other powers are major powers great
powers and middle powers but there is no
other superpower as of now china is the
aspiring super super power it the
chinese seek to display or to displace
the americans from their pedestal and
replace them as the sole superpower in
the world that is the great dream of the
chinese communist party and of shri xi
jinping
now when it comes to hypersonic missiles
yes the chinese did test some hypersonic
missile
recently it was a maneuvering mrv kind
of thing
but they are not the first country to
test the hypersonic missile
the russians have tested the sircon
missile which is about seven or which
which travels at seven or eight times
the speed of sound so it is a hypersonic
missile
so the russians are the first i believe
to have tested a hypersonic and the
chinese have now followed suit the
americans are scrambling to catch up
it is rumored that india may have some
hypersonic
plants that are being cooked up
something is in development it's been in
development for for a very long time in
india the thing is that you know once
you start a project it takes 10 20 years
for it to
produce the first testable
prototype india's plans
move forward at a glacial pace and it's
always because of lack of funding always
because of lack of funding
scientists and engineers want to test
test test you give them the funds they
will test every week test a new
configuration every week in india
nothing is happening it's just because
of lack of funds because
of whatever reason now so the chinese
are not the first the second country
that i can think of that have tested the
hypersonic missile the russian sir car
missile is the first one that i
know of it is
it is
good enough to bypass any nato defense
that's how fast it is
so the uh uk aircraft carriers that
they're i think they're building one or
two aircraft carriers they already
already obsolete in phase in the in the
when it comes to facing these missiles
now the chinese like you say they want
to annex taiwan can the us do anything
to stop china and exiting taiwan yes
the chinese will not make a move to a
next taiwan until they are 100 certain
that they will not fail
the chinese are extremely risk hours
in the past they have
done certain misadventures that have
cost them dearly in 1967 they tried to
repeat the 1962 war with india and they
were beaten back ignominiously it was a
terrible defeat for them but india's
media and historians will not speak
about this because it shows india in a
good light they have to keep showing
china in a good light and they have to
keep showing india as a nation of losers
and that's why you don't you don't know
about 1967. india defeated china in the
1967 war
but you don't know about it no one has
told you about this secondly in 1979 was
it the chinese tried to invade vietnam
they
had to face a disastrous defeat to the
vietnamese and these are very dangerous
things for the chinese communist party a
big military defeat today is almost
impossible to hide
right
and if such a thing happens then the
chinese communist party could lose
whatever
support they have among china's
population and you could see civil war
that's a possibility and that's why the
chinese are extremely risk hours they
will not try to invade taiwan they will
not make that move unless they are 100
certain that they are going to succeed
and right now they're not sure of that
so what can the us
do
to stop the chinese annexing taiwan they
need to keep up their presence in the
south china sea they need to keep up
their military naval presence in this
region
they need to
they need to invest in a stronger navy
they need to have submarines on patrol
in this region all the time
they need to have warships
going across the south china sea
traveling across this region all the
time they need to station aircraft
carriers there they need to try and
convert the quadrilateral dialogue the
so-called quad
into more of a formal alliance
if they can get india on board
if they can offer india what it seeks
you know there's always give and take
this there's no free lunch in the world
if the americans
seek
to turn the quad into a formal military
alliance
and if they want more participation more
robust participation from india they
need to give india what india seeks
i think they know what india seeks i
think you also know my audience my
friends what india seeks from the us
so the americans need to do that and
they also need to
ensure that the pressure is always on
on china the chinese should not be
allowed to become very over confident
right
so it and on also the diplomatic and
other maneuvers need to keep keep
happening uh china cannot be allowed to
just get away with all of its uh
peaceful rise projects
yeah and so on
so uh
so these are some of the things that can
happen that need to be done
to prevent china from making the move to
annex taiwan because if the chinese
succeed in next in taiwan
it's going to be a big big big problem
for not just the us but for india and
the rest of the world it's going to be a
huge problem and right now the chinese
are kind of
feeling the pinch their economy is
sliding backwards
there are shortages of coal and power
and other things maybe even food in
china
the economy is grinding to a stand stand
still after decades of double digit
growth you are having sub five uh sub uh
sub six percent sub five percent growth
in the chinese economy maybe the actual
figures are less than two percent if you
look through the misinformation that's
coming out of china and so on so the
chinese leadership may be getting
desperate
and they may try to grab for whatever
they can
before it's too late so we are currently
we may be passing through a dangerous
time the chinese may do something stupid
maybe in taiwan
maybe in tibet
on the india border so we need to be
extra vigilant right now india needs to
be extra vigilant
india needs to step up its game in the
indian ocean
and india needs to
counter every chinese move on the
northern border
so that's the situation we are in right
now
this is what what's known as interesting
times
arkadhar asks
[Laughter]
is intercast marriage good
should we do intercast marriage
go ahead who's stopping you
do it
i mean there's no law against
inter-caste marriage first of all let me
ask this question
sounds like a bengali name right
tell me what is the word for caste in
the vanguard
you what do you people like to call
bengali
it is known as wang gabasha from vanga
pradesh bangladesh which is bengal
so what is the word for caste in vanga
pasha
what is the word forecast in the kalinga
is there a word for caste
you could say varna you could say jaati
but these are two different terms with
two different meanings which is the word
for caste
is there a word forecast is there a word
forecast in marathi is there a word for
cast in punjabi is there a word for cast
in telugu is there a word for cast in
tamil
is there a word for cast in sanskrit
and the truth is that there is no word
for caste there is no synonym for the
word caste in any indian language we
have two terms varna and jaati which
have different meanings different
definitions different connotations and
the foreign european word caste
isn't found in any indian language and
therefore how is caste an indian thing
it is something that has been
superimposed upon indian society it is
something everybody has to follow today
because the government
mandates it it makes it mandatory for
your parents to write down something in
the field of caste when you fill up the
birth certificate and all all the forms
your school admission forms and
everything
you have to fill in something cast and
therefore everybody has to decide what
their caste is based on what the british
told your ancestors
but in indian society we didn't have
anything like caste we had varna and
jaati jathi is your bloodline your
petrolenial bloodline yeah yeah sure we
are a patriarchal country
patriarchal society show me a
matriarchal society somewhere else in
the world
so
your
your jaati is your bloodline
right now caste is supposed to be
blood-based right your you're bloodline
based but jati is
is is bloodline based jati is lineage
based when it comes to varna varna is
your occupation your aptitude whatever
you're best at
so in the harry potter universe verna is
what the the sorting hat tells you
in the harry potter universe also you
had forecasts
if you remember if any of you have seen
those
movies or read the books
so that is a european invention
those four schools
or four divisions
but in india we had varna via jati every
jathi could have the different vernas
even though you may be of the same
family the same blood the same lineage
you may have different
varnas you may be a shudra you may be
akshatri you may be a brahmana you may
be a vaishya
right
and when it comes to varna you could
have one within varna one warner
so this entire dogma of indians being
castessed
and following this forecast system is
utter nonsense it is something the the
colonialists imposed upon us they
created these four rigid divisions
and they forced indians to fit
themselves into these divisions if they
wanted government jobs
and soon or sooner sooner or later it
was bound to happen the entire indian
state started following this you want
any government documentation you have to
state what your caste is and only
forecasts are available
so this is a colonial invention you want
to marry from somebody some other
so-called caste go ahead mary i wish you
all the best my friend
have you seen people traveling in the
trains in kolkata in the metro in delhi
in the suburban trains in mumbai do you
see anyone giving a damn about what is
the cast of the person next to them
no one cares
have you gone to any restaurant in india
those busy restaurants cafeterias do you
see people wondering what is the cast of
the of the
of the uh
waiter or the cast of the chef no one
cares
no one practices castism in this country
it's absolute nonsense
yeah there are some parts in places in
rural india where the zamindari system
and the mughal
system and the other things they have
created certain traditions
but those are post
occupation traditions either after they
are they came into force either after
the turkic invasion and occupation of
india or either or then after the
british
invasion and occupation of india these
things were never practiced or followed
before
the invasions
of india one thousand years ago so
please understand this
we are not a caste society caste isn't
even a thing in our society today it is
because the indian state which is a
continuation of the british raj is
enforcing this nonsense india's
politicians are enforcing this nonsense
because
they gain electoral benefits from this
divide the society and rule the society
it is the british method
which india's politicians are today
exploiting and using
so please try and rise about above this
casteist nonsense there is no such thing
as caste you want to marry somebody
from whatever so-called caste he or she
is go ahead all the best sir
okay next question
this is by ayushman the question is was
bhagat singh a communist
excellent question so our wonderful
historians
will tell you that bhagat singh was a
great devout communist he was reading
what the communist manifesto or
something like that apparently
and he was a firm believer in communism
and he died a communist
lal salaam and so on and so forth
the irfan habibs the romula toppers the
prints the squints the whatever else is
scrolls froze whatever it is
they will all
tell you that bhagat singh was a
communist
okay fine so so let's say that yeah i
agree that
let's let's say what they're saying is
true
let's say that bhagat singh was reading
the communist manifesto let's say that
bhagat singh believed that he was a
communist at the time that he died
now here's the thing
when bhagat singh was hanged by the
british
he was 23 years old
how old he was 23
let me tell you
something when i was 23 years old
i was clueless
i had read a lot of books i thought i
knew everything about history i thought
i knew everything about the world
but looking back today
i was clueless
i had not the least amount of idea of
how the world worked
i did not know what politics was i
didn't know what propaganda was i did
not know the truth about the various
ideologies of politics
and i did not know
the patterns that underlie all the
history books that i had read i
understood nothing i was clueless
when i was 23 i thought i had the world
figured out
right
when you are 18 when you are 23 when
you're 25 you think that you understand
everything but as you grow a little
older i can tell you today
you realize that you are really really
silly and clueless
it is a phase that everybody has to pass
through
without exception
right
so let's say bhagat singh
died at the age of 23 and at that time
he was reading the communist manifesto
had he not been hanged by the british
by the age of 40 who would have been
something else
he would have given up on communism
after he would have understood what
communism really is
bhagat singh was a patriot
he was a brilliant patriotic young man
who gave up his life
for his mother land he was a patriot he
put his motherland before his own life
do you know what india's communists are
like
the indian communist parties various
communist groups organizations they are
all without exception
what are they
they are anti-nationals
do you think after bhagat singh realized
this he would have remained a communist
the guy died at the age of 23
23 is too young
to have a political ideology for life 23
is the time when you are experimenting
with different things okay let me try
this let me see how it feels let me do
it for a year now i don't like it now
i'll try something else
you are experimenting you're trying to
figure the world out you think you've
got things figured out and then after
you realize that was wrong let me try
something else and that is the phase he
was passing through but one thing is
very clear he was
a complete total 100 percent all in
patriot
and that itself tells you that he would
have never agreed with the ideology that
the com the indian communist parties in
whichever incarnation you find them what
the ideology that they follow they are
without
they are without exception all
anti-nationals
they will support china's agenda over
india's national interest they will
support pakistan's agenda over india's
national interest they will support the
western agenda above india's national
interest no matter what it is they will
not support india's national interest
they will try and denigrate india
they will write terrible things about
india in the western newspapers in the
western media
they will support the chinese communist
parties territorial claims over india
they will said that the chinese
chairman is our chairman chairman mao is
our chairman and so on and so forth many
of them acted as spies for the soviet
union
and spies for the for the chinese
communist party and for various western
powers you think bhagat singh would ever
have done that
and that is why bhagat singh
would never have continued continued
with communism had he been allowed to
live on past the age of 23
that is this is as simple and clear as
day
all right
next question
yuvraj says what are your views on the
recent threats
given to pakistan by isis khorasan is
there any threat to india due to the
this extreme radicalization
see isis isis harassan is is one of the
one of the
lesser terrorist organizations in the
bigger scheme of things the biggest
terrorist organization is the taliban
which is which the pakistanis created in
order to
take over afghanistan as of now they
have succeeded isis k is not a very big
deal when it comes to the bigger scheme
of things
is there any threat to india because of
the radicalization by isis k
listen
there is a huge threat to india and that
threat is from pakistan and nowhere else
nowhere else the only threat to india is
pakistan the isi the pakistani army it
is not taliban it is not isis it is not
isis k it is not isis j it doesn't it is
not isis q or whatever else they have
the only threat to india is pakistan on
the western front
so that is the only uh threat that india
needs to worry about we have to deal
with pakistan in the next five to 10
years and deal with this problem once
and for all in a permanent fashion
that's what needs to happen you solve
that problem all other problems get
solved automatically
so that is the thing that's what needs
to happen uh is this a big problem for
pakistan no it's not a big problem for
pakistan the real problem for pakistan
is pashtun nationalism which is going to
emerge in the next two three years
from afghanistan the taliban is a
pashtun
organization the taliban is a pashtun
nationalist organization yes they follow
the path of radical islam and so on and
so forth
but they are not primarily an islamist
organization they are primarily a
pashtun nationalist organization
organization and
there is a huge unfinished agenda
between pashtunistan afghanistan and
pakistan pakistan currently is an
occupation of a significant portion of
pashtun majority territory territory
that should buy all
by by should with a great deal of
justification be part of afghanistan so
there is a huge territorial dispute
there and that is going to
come to the fore sooner or later give it
two years three years
i would say three years at most and then
let's see how it goes for pakistan
i think the biggest threat to pakistan
is the taliban itself right now they are
making all the right moves they are
trying to uh
they are trying to pack the taliban
leadership with their own
hand-picked leaders but let's see how
long that lasts
let's see how
there is a certain property of certain
animals that they you cannot tame them
you cannot you can
you can
herd a group of sheep
but you can't herd cats
and similarly you can't herd snakes
so let's see i wish the isi all the best
because in the next two three years it's
gonna be fun and games
for us to watch
okay arnov asks a lot of questions are
being raised about against mr jinnah but
you once said that he was a true patriot
in the beginning how and why
now this is an interesting question
let's see every every individual has a
you have to treat their life you have to
examine their life with a great deal of
nuance
so when it comes to mr jinnah mr jinnah
was born um
he was born in sindh was he he was a
gujarati i think from saurashtra
originally
um
his grandfather had converted to islam
it was either a rajput or a cathy or
something like that
and
yeah so so that's that's his birth
and he was very much like i said
uh
at the forefront of the indian
freedom struggle the freedom
the struggle to break free from british
now jinnah was
educated in
in england
he was very much
an anglophile
he was a non-religious person
he was in favor
of a free india
he spent a great
great portion of his early career
fighting for india's independence in one
way or the other he was a lawyer and he
assisted
indian freedom fighters and their legal
cases and so on that's what i read
and he was in favor of hindu muslim
unity he was a genuine secularist
not the kind of secularism that you find
in india today which is uh hindu phobia
essentially he was a genuine secularist
he said he was of the opinion that
hinduism
but islam etc should be treated the same
and hindus and muslims should
work together for a free united india
that was
very much
his political ideology
he even opposed the formation of the
muslim league saying that it would cause
uh
it was it would it would cause
communal communion communalization and
fragmentation of india society so he
opposed the formation of the muslim
league
so yeah if you look at these actions of
his not his words but his actual actions
those are the actions of a patriot
so he was
initially
a patriot he was an indian nationalist
he was in favor of freedom for india
from the british he wanted a unified
india he wanted hindus and muslims to
work together and live together for
india's freedom and
live together in a unified
free
country
in free india that was
his stand for a very long time then then
what happened was that the british
parachuted mohandas gandhi into india
from south africa and overnight he
became the mega star in the congress
party jinnah was part of the congress
party and he suddenly found himself
completely marginalized
see
jinnah had an agenda that was not quite
in tune with the british plans for india
so they brought in somebody like mr
gandhi who was totally in aligned with
the british agenda and mr jinnah found
himself completely sidelined and
marginalized he quit the congress party
at some stage
and he went into exile he lived in
england for a decade or so
and over there he had a certain
flash of inspiration
and he said that listen if if you go
down sideline me i'm gonna go and stab
you in the back so he came back to india
joined the muslim league or he joined
the muslim league before i'm not sure
exactly you can look it up you know you
can open a book and look it up but then
he came back to india and then he
started working for the breakup of india
so because he was not able to uh
get
the political uh
whatever he wanted politically he was
not able to get the political prominence
he desired
that he thought he deserved
because of that he turned his back to
india and he stabbed india in the back
and he
ended up helping the british and mr
gandhi
worked towards the partition of india
so he started off as a patriot but then
he betrayed his own conscience his own
cause and his own people and his own
country
so that's
mr jinnah in a nutshell
spider-man says why did the french
support india's nuclear tests despite
the whole world being against it what
are the french
geopolitical interests
you see the french have
a very different geopolitical outlook as
compared to the us and nato the french
are very much i think a part of nato i
think they are yes
and yet they see themselves as a
distinct culture distinct civilization
they do not see themselves as being part
of the anglo sphere
the anglosphere is the five eyes
countries
the us canada uk australia and new
zealand these are the five closely knit
countries they work together very
closely they don't trust outsiders they
are
except for australia and new zealand
those are part of part of nato
i think i'm not sure if canada is part
of nato but but you get the picture
right
so the french see themselves as a as a
distinct civilization
in if you look at europe's history
the french have one of the oldest
cultures in europe starting from the
franks
charlemagne and so on right
so they
see themselves as having a superior and
distinct culture
and they
have consistently refused to toe the
line of the
english-speaking countries
and they also have significant interests
in the indian ocean region they they're
they own
the the island of reunion which is in
the indian ocean near the seychelles
and and they need to they want to ensure
that that stays in their uh
within their jurisdiction they don't
lose control of that place
and that's why they have a significant
naval presence in the indian ocean they
have
uh submarines
they have a at least one aircraft
carrier and there are nuclear weapons
power and so on so their outlook their
worldview is different
and that's why
when
india
tested five nuclear weapons in 1998 the
entire world condemned india's nuclear
tests but the french refused to condemn
the tests
i think the indian foreign affairs
minister or
defense secretary or somebody actually
went to france
met
the french president jacques iraq and
i think there was a good amount of
synergy and understand mutual
understanding at that point
and from that point onwards france and
india have had a very close strategic
partnership even today the french are
very supportive of india and india is
also very supportive of france and so on
so the french world view is different
their geopolitical interests are
different very different from the us
their interests are in the indian ocean
region their interests are in
maintaining their sovereignty from the
anglo-sphere
they want to maintain their distinct
culture and all which kind of is being
eroded by their other actions and so on
but that's a different topic so that's
why so that's the reason why the french
have supported india's nuclear tests and
that's why india and france are very
close and very strong strategic
partnership i would never characterize
geopolitical
relationships as friendships
but it's a very close relationship and a
very warm relationship whenever you see
the indian prime minister and the french
president meet you can see that there is
genuine warmth
in the relationship
so that is a brief
background of why it is so
why did the sanskrit language vanish
from india the sanskrit language
vanished from india beginning in the
19th century the in the indian state
which was then the british raj the east
india company or
so so what happened was that
india's education system was entirely in
sanskrit
india's temples universities everywhere
you had education you had sanskrit being
taught so everybody
learned sanskrit everybody could
understand sanskrit everybody could
speak sanskrit but their primary means
of communication would be whatever was
their mother tongue north south east
west in other places you had different
languages so everybody would know their
mother tongue and they would know
sanskrit that's how it was until the
first half of the 19th century or even
the second half of the 19th century
then the british imposed their foreign
education system upon india and they
said that if you want a government job
you need to know how to speak english
and you need to have a degree
which we have given to you
and the medium of
education was english
in this education system which they
impose upon india
and
slowly but steadily indians started
needing these government jobs because
the british destroyed india's industries
and everything so the only means of
livelihood that was eventually available
to indians was government jobs so
everybody had to start going through the
india the british education system
and that's why people started losing
touch with sanskrit and they also
destroyed india's indigenous education
system the temples based education
system which was recorded very
meticulously by the rampal in
in the beautiful tree in his book the
beautiful tree
so that is the beginning of the
uprooting of sanskrit from india it is
the beginning of
sanskrit going out of usage
and after independence the
indian state which was the successor of
the british raj continued this and made
it even worse
and that's why sanskrit has vanished
from india today very few people speak
or understand sanskrit
it is actually very easy to revive
sanskrit very easy it can happen within
20 years but there is no political will
because there is nothing to be gained
politically from doing this
and that's why the governments want to
do it until we have the right kind of
leadership someday in the future
so that is in brief why sanskrit
vanished from india the indian state did
that
harshit says if there are multiple
evidences that prove that shivkar bapuji
talpade made an aircraft eight years
before the wright brothers
so why do we still give credit to the
white brothers for the first aircraft
interesting question so i have also
heard these stories that uh
that
shivkar bapuji talpade was the first
person to fly a heavier than air
aircraft
mechanized unmanned aircraft
on the beaches of mumbai
a few years before the wright brothers
did it i think it was in 1895 or
something like that so that's what i've
heard i tried to look for the evidence
where can i find real evidence for this
can i find a photograph of the airplane
which he flew can i find a story that
was written at that time a newspaper
report a journalistic report can i find
something
some piece of primary evidence i was
able to find nothing
now what does this tell us
so so when you say that there is
multiple
there are multiple pieces of evidence
where are those multiple pieces of
evidence there are lots of people who
say this happened
but where is the evidence is there a
photograph of this guy doing this thing
is there the plane somewhere that we can
see and see if that that model can be
recreated and can it fly
is there a newspaper report a
journalistic report from the title
nothing but that thing is available
now does it mean that this doesn't
happen did not happen no
it could very well have happened
but if the evidence existed it has been
taken care of it's been destroyed
so either there are so there are two
possibilities a this is a myth it never
happened b
it actually happened but all the
evidence has been
wiped out has been destroyed
so i don't know what is the truth
i have looked for the evidence i have
never been able to find the
evidence but it is certainly possible
that an engineer in india could have
been able to fly a plane before these
individuals right brothers did it it is
certainly possible
why is it so hard to imagine that it
could it would have happened
it certainly could have happened it's
not a very big leap of technology
the principles are very simple
so it could certainly have happened but
we have lost the evidence if it actually
happened so what can i say about it
and that's why the credit is given to
the wright brothers maybe
maybe this was deliberately destroyed
all the evidence so that the credit
keeps going to the west and not to india
it's possible but it's just speculation
i don't have any evidence to say this
so the truth is that there is no
evidence today
but it doesn't mean it never happened it
may have happened but we do not have the
evidence so please don't say we have
evidence if you have evidence please
show me please show me the evidence
i will be the happiest person in the
world if you can show me the evidence
all right so it's very simple
it is not a criticism of anybody
the simple fact is that we don't not
have the evidence
and i wish the evidence was there i will
be the happiest person in the world if
any of you
can show me actual evidence that this
event actually happened
atharva says
is india the only real civilization left
in the world since the greeks romans
nors etc
got replaced brutally by christianity
chinese civilization was destroyed by
communism is egyptian civilization
destroyed by islamic invasions
and many more
should we be proud of this thing that
even after so many invasions we are
still a dharmic country with millennia
old civilization
okay
interesting question good question
first of all
let us define civilization what is
civilization
does your history textbook teach you
what is a civilization
does your history teacher tell you what
a civilization is no
they don't
so let me explain what a civilization is
a civilization is a very advanced
society
that practices its indigenous culture
that has a very evolved culture and has
its constitution its laws
and its institutions that are based
rooted in its indigenous cultures values
and principles
it should also have a very advanced
economy a very prosperous economy very
high standards of living it should have
a sphere of economic and military
influence that far exceeds its
geographical
boundaries that is what i define as a
civilization
and by this definition india is no
longer a civilization india is merely
a mediocre nation state
india's institutions india's
constitution india's laws
are
western in origin there is nothing
indigenous
about
india's institutions india's laws
india's constitution india's policies
india's governance anything at all it's
all foreign
india's medium of education is english
mostly
you go to go go to a job interview
you're going to have to speak in english
everything is foreign in india how can
you call that a civilization
so please understand that the indian
civilization died in 1947. until 1947 we
were trying to
reinstate india civilization in 1947
the indian republic was codified
in an adharmic fashion
and therefore the indian civilization
officially died at the time it doesn't
mean it can't come back
it can come back
but
it will take some doing
so india is currently no longer a
civilization the civilization has died
it can come back but it's currently dead
secondly are we still a dharmic country
are we still dharmic country really
are india's laws dharmic laws
is india's constitution dharmic in
nature
is india's governance dharmic
are india's policies dharmic
is india's
education system dharmic india is an
adharmic country it is the opposite of
dharmic so please understand my friends
it is nice that we are still here
it is nice that we still know what we
were like but we are no longer a
civilization and we are now in a dharmic
republic republic
so that is what we need to resist we
need to fight against and we need to
rebuild
what we really can be that's what needs
to happen
but let's not congratulate ourselves for
what we have not achieved
samprathi goes for me says my teacher
said that in the vedic times the
learning system was only about
memorizing
sir was our
vedic learning system
only dependent on memorizing things
or was there any research or practical
learning techniques
involved in that
well your teacher
what can i say about your teacher
okay so when it comes to the vedic times
there was a certain aspect of him of
memorization
when it comes to
the vedas you were supposed to memorize
the vedas
but everybody isn't supposed to memorize
only those who go into a certain line of
work
let's say our religious scholars they
were supposed dharmic scholars
they were supposed to memorize the vedas
and various sutras the same goes in the
buddhist sutras and all you're supposed
to memorize these
but can you memorize mathematics
you can't memorize mathematics
mathematics is logic you have to
internalize the logic you have to solve
problems indians
invented mathematics
and in mathematics there is no
memorization
so how can a teacher claim there was
memorizing in
everything was about memorizing indians
were at the forefront of mathematics of
technology of research and development
look at the cities of the of the uh
region the saraswati hindu uh era of our
culture
can you see the incredible geometry the
incredible architecture can you imagine
what sort of geometrical understanding
we would have needed advanced geometry
advanced hydroengineering all this
can't be done by memorizing things
you have to understand the concepts you
have to calculate
angles and equations and volumes
right
so science is not about memorization
indians were at the forefront of
astronomy for instance can you memorize
the stars which are ever changing there
is no memorization
in astronomy
and then you had the creative arts
you had great playwrights like bhasa
kali dasa etc where is the memorization
in that this is creative work there is
no memorization involved in that so your
teacher i regret to say is a complete
fool
and that is something that is that's a
condition that's prevalent among many
teachers in india many teachers are
really good of course
but the majority seem to be like this
ignorant fools you know
so that's what i have to say about this
it is completely untrue that the vedic
learning system was all about blind
memorization and indians were just
idiots who were just memorizing things
and going about their lives like robots
it was not the case
the
opposite
is true
okay
usual says
according to the people of manipur a
sage from sileth in present-day bengal
bangladesh went to banipur and converted
their king and people to hinduism after
burning their manipuri folk religions
holy books the holy books of sadamahisam
the puyas is this true
and if it is true does it not prove that
ancient hindus disrespected ancient
religions
all right
a good question good question very good
at least the first part of the question
is very good
so what is the history of hinduism in
manipur
so the the person you are referring this
individual his name was shanti das gosai
he was from bengal was he from silat
maybe maybe i'm not sure but he was from
bengal for sure and he went to manipur
he was a preacher of of gaudi or
vaisnavism
and the king of manipur at the time his
name was pameba
he was the grandfather of ching tang
kumba bhaga chandra
so pam iba was the king under the who
under the influence of this guy
shantidas gosai
declared
gaudiya vaishnavism to be the official
culture or religion if you want to call
it
of manipur
and he ordered the burning
of the holy books of the sannamahi
tradition
which is the uh which is the indigenous
culture religion whatever you want to
call it of
the kingdom of manipur of the of the
region of manipur
so this king under the influence of
shantidas gosai
declared gaudiya vaishnavism to be the
state religion and he had these holy
books the pujas
burned
some pujas did survive some of them have
been found but they they are unable to
translate them because manipur
historians are all idiots by now they
don't know how to
read their ancestral language
but some books have survived but now the
thing is this
did gaudi or vaishnavism enter manipur
only during the time of shantidas gosai
in ching and this guy
the king parmaiba was there no hinduism
or vaishnavism in manipur before that
what nonsense
vaishnavism had had a presence in
manipur for a very long time before that
there were temples version of temples
built in manipur before
this king palmeiba was even even born
before
uh shantidas gosia was even born
the
the very first
recorded
influence of hinduism and manipur was
from southern india there were these
saints called the alavars
from tamil nadu
it was their influence that came into
manipur before gaudiya vaishnavism ever
came into manipur
and there was no conversion by force or
anything it was just
influence
i mean manipur is very much part of the
indian subcontinent
the influence of indian culture went all
the way to the philippines thailand
burma cambodia vietnam laos china japan
korea everywhere so clearly there will
be influence in manipur as well and
there was never never any force there
was never there was never any compulsion
the kings tolerated it they did not care
they did not have any objection to the
presence of vaishnavism or hinduism of
any sort in manipur there was no issue
like that
it was only during the star the time of
this guy palmeira under the influence of
shantidas gosai that this stupid thing
was done
that the pujas were burned and that is
something that the communists etc
try to portray as
uh
as an instance of hinduism being
oppressive to indigenous traditions and
all that the thing is that it was the
king himself who ordered this under the
influence of this individual this fellow
called shantidas gosai
so yeah this happened this did happen
and it is unfortunate
it was
terrible that these books were burned
and i blame the king for this i don't
blame shantidas gosari for burning the
books
the king could have rejected
this guy's advice he could have had the
guy executed if he wanted but the king
himself decided that the book should be
burned so it is entirely the fault of
the manipuri king pam iba that the books
were burned
so you can't blame hinduism for this no
no no tell me something
india is a country with 1.3 billion
population right the question is does it
not prove that ancient hindus
disrespected indigenous religions
so india is a country with 1.3 billion
people let's say a hindu goes and
commits murder tomorrow
murders happen in every country right
let's say hindu goes and commits more
does it mean that all hindus are
murderers
let's say hindu goes and commits a
robbery somewhere tomorrow does it mean
that all hindus are robbers
do you understand what i am saying if
one person does something stupid or
silly or something criminal does it mean
that everybody is a criminal
this is the problem in people's thinking
please
try to
learn critical thinking
if somebody if one person did something
stupid it doesn't mean that all hindus
are like that that all ancient hindus
disrespected indigenous religions
that is utter nonsense
so that's my answer
avinash kali says do the constellations
look the same from other planets
so the constellations
which avinash is talking about are the
configurations of the stars we call them
in sanskrit we have certain names for
them in latin they have some other names
so we have the subtershi constellation
which the westerners called ursa major
the big dipper or whatever and we have
various other constellations other
configurations of stars that are quite
visible and they resemble either animal
or human figures or something or other
like that you know
so those are called constellations
and that's something that the ancients
have
dreamt up you could say they it is the
human nature to imagine shapes in
everything
familiar shapes and everything so that's
how the constellations were born and
these constellations have names
so do the constellations look the same
from other planets so from the earth
these
shapes have a certain pattern let's say
i go to mars will it look different
let's say i go to pluto
will it look different from there i
don't think the constellations will look
very different from other planets
because we are still within the solar
system
and the vantage the vantage point that
we have is still very much the same
but if we were to go toward neighboring
star let's say the
proxima centauri system or tau seatai
for instance which is about 10 light
years 10 11 light years from here then
the constellations would look different
yes
but from within the solar system i think
it would look very much
the same because it's still a very small
piece of the
cosmic real estate it's all
in one location only even though it may
be very far for us
so the answer is no they will not look
this uh they will very much look the
same from other planets but they will
look different when you go to another
star system
next question
the question is the original
indo-european world was more connected
than the christian european dominance
world
persians when threatened by arabs rent
to bharat the power says yes
do you think the ancient indo-europeans
had an idea about their origins
from our land from india
and the proof hasn't been found because
the abrahamics made sure that no history
survives as it is all considered to be
lies
i i think that the ancient
indo-europeans across eurasia did have
an idea of where they had migrated for
from
i'm not sure they remembered where
exactly the land lied maybe they would
say it was from the east and maybe they
had a name for the land
now let me show you something extremely
interesting let me share the screen
all right where are we one second
so i am
can you see this i'm not sure you can
see this hanging there one second
okay you can see my screen now so let me
let me type in the name of croatia
let us
google croatia and let's go to wikipedia
now as i keep saying wikipedia is not a
reliable source of information but in
this case for the sake of
for the sake of conserving time let's go
to wikipedia
so this is croatia right now let's go to
etymology of croatia what is the origin
of the name of croatia the name of
croatia derives from the medieval latin
croatia
itself a derivation of northwest slavic
whose origin is horwath
from proposed proto-slavic whatever that
is which possibly comes from the old
person
so the old persian word
was the origin of the modern nation the
name of the nation of croatia now they
are stopping here and they will not tell
you what is the origin of the old
persian word
the origin of the old persian word
is the sanskrit word saraswat or
saraswati
because saw becomes ha
when you translate from from sanskrit to
old persian because sanskrit was a
mother language
of old persian
so this tells you
that the nation of croatia
is named after the ancient river
saraswati
so it's clear that even though they do
not remember perhaps
what the origin of their people is
and yet
the origin of the people
geographical origin is still encoded in
the name of the country
and i am certain that before the
christianization of the european of the
indo-european world
i am certain that they actually would
have remembered where they came from
so you are right the
the original indo-european world was
much more connected than the christian
european world today
all the ancient knowledge was destroyed
once everyone was converted to
christianity all the books were
destroyed all the books were burned
all the wise women were burned alive as
witches and so on and people were
rendered illiterate the only language
that they were allowed to learn was
latin in addition to the
their mother tongue
and all writing was in latin
and the only book you were allowed to
read was that the bible right and so on
so that's how the
ancient knowledge was wiped out
and yet
in this in the example of croatia the
origin the geographical origin of the
people of this country is encoded in the
name of the country itself isn't that
fascinating
okay neil mehta asks
what are your views on grigori perelman
solving the
conjecture and then rejecting the one
million dollar prize and refusing the
fields medal too
i read that he was disappointed by the
response of the scientific community
about his research could you please shed
some more light on it
this is again a very interesting uh
topic grigori perelman was is is sorry i
apologize he is
a russian mathematician
who solved this great
more than a century old year old problem
the punk array conjecture i'll not go
into what it is but he saw this enormous
problem that so many people had tried to
solve and nobody was had succeeded in
doing it
so he solved this problem he was give he
was offered the millennium price i think
which has a one million dollar
prize money he refused that he also
refused the fields metal in mathematics
which is given once in four years to one
person who is below 40. so it is even
greater than the nobel prize the field's
medal he refused that too
and uh like you said he was disappointed
by the response of the scientific
community about his research so let's
understand what that was what was the
thing that he was disappointed with
uh let me share my screen once again
i will
show you something interesting
so we were looking at croatia now let's
go back to google
let's go to
an article called manifest
destiny
this is an article that came out in
um
sorry not manifest destiny manifold
destiny
any fold destiny this is an article that
came out in the new yorker magazine
in 2006 the author was sylvia naser who
wrote
the very famous book called a beautiful
mind
so she wrote this article in which she
she revealed
how the chinese mathematician
yao
tried to steal the credit
for solving this
problem from grigori perelman what
happened was that gregory paralman did
not submit his proof of the flank array
conjecture to any peer-reviewed journal
he simply put it up on the
physics archive server which is a
pre-print server so the papers that are
put up there are not peer reviewed he
simply put up his paper there
and that was it so it did not go through
peer review
it confounded mathematicians
and then soon enough you find that this
guy shin tung yao
along with a couple of other chinese
mathematicians
produced a paper
which they called the crowning
achievement or crowning something or the
other in solving the prakhar conjecture
and they essentially tried to steal the
credit credit for solving this problem
from gregory perelman
and then it as it happens
an indian mathematician an indian uh
an indian graduate student i think he
examined both the papers
and he
exposed
how much of this material was just copy
pasted from gregory perelman's work
and that's how these chinese
mathematicians including this very
famous guy
shin tangiao they were exposed
but this greatly disappointed grigori
permanent so this this article manifold
destiny is the story of how this
happened how this attempted
theft happened and what was the
aftermath of that it's very interesting
you should read it
so that is why gregory perelman was
deeply bitterly disappointed in the
response of the scientific community
essentially how these people try to
steal the credit and all that happened
after that
and
that essentially led to him leaving the
field of mathematics altogether
after solving the problem he just
stepped out of the world of mathematics
and i think he has not been active ever
since and he has rejected every honor
that has been offered to him every prize
money everything
so he is a you could say a pure
mathematician a pure scientist who is
doing it just for the sake
of solving the problems and not for the
sake of any prize money or any financial
or any other recognition an incredible
person
one in a billion kind of person gregory
parent one of the greatest
mathematicians one of the greatest
living mathematicians and probably
one of the greatest mathematicians of
all time very interesting
very interesting
all right next question
anshul says you always say that under
one strong leader india can be unified
and become a strong nation
what were the common leadership traits
or qualities amongst all the great
historical leaders like
shivaji maharaj chandragupta maurya and
others can and how can we develop such
leadership
qualities
right so leadership is a
fascinating topic
it's a very simple topic
at one end of the spectrum
it's a very complex topic when we peel
back several layers
and and look under the hood
so what are the common traits or
qualities between
amongst people like the great
chatropathy
shivaji maharaj chandragupta maurya and
people like kaneshka
and so on and so forth the great great
leaders the great rulers of india
so there are a couple of things you will
you will notice straight away
they understood what the national
interest was
and they put the national interest above
everything else they put their the
national interest about their personal
likes and dislikes and their personal
pet ideologies and all of that the
national interest comes first the
national interest is simply the long
term security and prosperity of the
nation and its people that's as simple
as it is security and prosperity long
term not today not next week
next 500 years
that kind of that kind of uh
vision is required if not the next 500
years next 50 hundred years at least you
have to look at as a great leader so
that is one thing they had in common
they put the national interest above
everything else
and that is in contrast with somebody
like mohandas gandhi
who put his pet ideology of non-violence
above the national interest
right so that is the difference between
great leaders and
fake leaders
so that is something shattered
and the the great cholas had
and so on and so forth there is one
thing the other thing is they understood
the teachings
of the great vishnu gupta and they
followed those teachings right
uh
more or less more or less yes they did
so you cannot
if you contrast that with
the behavior of somebody like pratyura
johan
who allowed
the enemy of the civilization
to go away
who who allowed the
who forgave the enemy of the
civilization and allowed him to go to
return to his homeland
regroup and come back
so that is something that is an action
that goes against the
precepts and the teachings of vishnu
because that is something that is going
to
harm the nation
and its
interests in the long run
so that is the behavior you don't want
in a leader the kind of behavior that uh
prithviraj chohan demonstrated that rani
nayaki devi demonstrated that's the kind
of leadership which is not leadership
that is
harmful to the nation
etc
they understood
statecraft chanakiniti and all that so
these are some of the qualities that are
common in all great leaders
and that's the kind of leadership we
would like to see in the future that is
the kind of leadership that will take
the country the nation the civilization
forward
if you look at the past 70 years i'm not
like i'm not talking about the 21st
century let's just talk about the 20th
century you hardly had any leader who
did that
after our so-called independence
whether it is the great shri nehru the
great mr gandhi or
individuals who came after them
uh i mean you know what i mean right so
so that is something that was lacking in
all these people and hopefully in the
future we will
have leaders who will surpass
every previous leader
so how do you develop such leadership
qualities first study what leadership is
and then it's all about discipline
discipline and living a disciplined life
first you have to first discipline
yourself
and
cultivate all those qualities in you
and then you have to
find a way
of taking other people forward with you
if you have the ability to do that
so that is what leadership is in a very
small nutshell it's a very big topic you
can
you can have an entire series of
documentaries about that it's a very big
topic but in short that's what it is
okay one more question
spider-man says has russia fallen as
said by abhijit mitra
he says that china is the big brother of
russia and putin is a chinese puppet
okay listen i have not heard
mr ayamitra say this
so uh therefore i would not like to
comment about what he he may or may not
have said i have not heard that and
therefore i'm not gonna answer that part
of the question now is china the big
puppet
the big
the big brother of russia is mr putin a
chinese puppet no absolutely not
mr putin is nobody's puppet mr putin
mr putin will be nobody's puppet he
understands what he understands what the
national interest of russia is
and he is doing whatever needs to be
done
with the resources that he has at his
disposal
it is very well known that russia is no
longer a superpower
it is not most likely not even a top ten
economy
its
economy is dependent on natural
resources oil and gas and coal and all
that
it has
a very powerful nuclear nuclear arsenal
the most powerful nuclear answer in the
world so it has certain strengths it has
certain weaknesses it has one of the
weaknesses is its enormous
geographical extent
much of which could be considered to be
undefended and the chinese have their
eyes on that
so truth be told mr putin is the
opposite of china's puppet he doesn't
trust china china and russia have a very
fraught history the russians almost
nuked china in the 1960s and there is a
big territorial dispute that is
currently that has currently been swept
under the carpet but it's going to rear
its ugly head sooner or later
so right now because the west is so much
anti-russia
the chinese and the russians are kind of
working together you could consider them
to be semi-allies of some of some kind
but if you were to believe that mr putin
trusts the chinese that is
entirely
and completely
incorrect mr putin knows what the
chinese want
he knows what the long-term agendas and
plans are
he knows their ambitions and he knows
the territory the russian territory that
the chinese covet
that they have their eyes on
and so on so
mr putin is currently doing whatever he
can to keep things going
and in the future hopefully
things will be better for russia and
not so better for the chinese which will
be good for the whole world so i would
not
say that china is the big brother of
russia it would appear to some people to
be so at a superficial level
china has a much stronger economy
so that makes it looks like the chinese
are richer and therefore big brothers
but the russians have a bigger
and more powerful nuclear arsenal in a
much
more powerful
military in a very
battle-tested military
as opposed to the chinese military which
is completely untested so i think it's
more like a balance of equals the
russians are way stronger militarily and
the chinese are much more stronger
economically so it's an interesting
balance
but i would not consider the chinese to
have a big big brotherly relationship
with the russians and especially with mr
putin mr putin is nobody's puppet
tanvir sheikh says what are the possible
ways to
achieve artificial gravity
would big fans in a starship ceiling to
create a downward push
work
um
no i i
can't imagine how a big fan would create
a downward push or create gravity
the
the simplest way to create artificial
gravity in space in earth orbit or
beyond
is to have a donut shaped
ring shaped spacecraft which is rotating
around its
center
so that creates
an artificial gravity like situation if
you have a string and a cup which is
dangling from the string
you pour
water in the cup and then you whirl the
cup around it's going to create an
artificial gravity kind of thing and the
water will stay in the cup even when
it's upside down
so that's the kind of thing we're
talking about that's the easiest way to
create
artificial gravity
right centrifugal force
so that's what needs to have but that's
the easiest way to create artificial
gravity
in orbit around the earth or beyond
and such concepts and designs have been
explored extensively in science fiction
let me show you
uh if any such uh
there's a lot of artwork i'm sure that's
available
let's take a look at this artificial
let's see
so can you see the structure here
so this ring-like structure
this one here this one here this one
here it would have to rotate
and that will create an artificial
gravity like situation within
you could even have
an enormous such structure
a cylindrical structure
like
what you see here and so on it would
have to keep rotating and that would
create the artificial gravity
on the surface on the inner surface of
the cylinder or the
or the
toroidal structure so that is the
simplest and easiest way
of creating artificial
gravity in a spacecraft
yuvraj says why is the brahmaputra
called a male river in india may be the
only one in india is there any
historical significance to that i i
found this very interesting question
uh rivers have masculine and feminine
names
i don't think the brahmaputra is the
only river in india which has a
masculine name
i can think of at least one more river
the damodar river i think it's also in
the east of india
uh which also has a masculine name
damodar is one of the names of lord
krishna
now as we know the the word for river in
sanskrit is nadi which is a feminine
name
which is a feminine word
in sanskrit words have genders
and nadi has the feminine gender there
are many indo-european languages in
which you have
gendered nouns right for example french
in french the word for river is rivier
which is again a feminine
noun
and i imagine i think that
many of the rivers in europe also have
feminine names
for example the river seine in france la
seine it is a feminine name
the river thames
which flows through london its original
name was tamesa
which is the dark river from sanskrit
tamas
tamesa is a feminine name again
and then you have a whole bunch of
rivers named after the river goddess
dhanu the rigvedix river goddess dhanu
which are all situated in eastern europe
dawn knight danube donates
etc
so these are all named after a river
goddess a feminine female goddess again
and in india also
most rivers seem to have feminine names
it's a very interesting thing and i'm i
don't have an answer for this i don't
know why it is so
it is something that is quite
fascinating
and
it needs to be looked into
in more detail by historians if they
ever will do that
and it's it's it would tell a lot about
india's culture actually why have all
most of the rivers been given feminine
names carved
godavari ganga saraswati yamuna which is
yummy tapati
and many more most of the rivers seem to
have feminine names very interesting
so yeah it's something that needs to be
looked at in
with a great deal of seriousness but so
far nobody seems to have asked this
question at least no historian seems to
have asked this question of themselves
so i don't have an answer for you but i
certainly agree that it's a fascinating
question it's a fascinating topic
and something that extends far beyond
europe
beyond india into the entire
indo-european
uh region so something that needs to be
looked at
in detail in depth
great me says what was the actual reason
of the bengal famines was it due to the
scorched scorched earth policy of the
british
due to the fear of the japanese conquest
or due to natural reasons or due to both
of these the answer is none of these
the famines that the british engineered
in india had nothing to do with the
japanese conquest or or a potential
japanese conquest the japanese were on
the doorstep of india in the 1940s
the british started their artificial
farmings engineering these artificial
famines from the 1700s onwards
it had nothing to do with japan and
there was no scorched earth policy
and there was no natural reasons these
were artificial famines
the british understood that
the indians were great fighters they
were able to
uh
survive
the centuries of turkic occupation and
and oppression
and maintain their culture and they kept
fighting indians kept fighting indians
kept resisting so the british decided to
just starve the indians you can't fight
if you are dying of hunger
you can't stand if you're dying of
hunger let alone fight so the british
decided to starve india into submission
so you had these artificial farmings
year after year after year
more than 100 million indians died in
these artificial famines
at least 100 million indians died in
these artificial famines that the
british engineered it had nothing to do
with the japanese it had nothing to do
with natural natural reasons these were
artificially engineered
famines they engineered them in a
variety of ways they forced farmers to
start growing indigo and cash crops
instead of food stock food crops for
instance that's one way of doing it and
there's a multitude of other ways of
doing such things
the end result is that more than at
least minimum 100 million indians died
as a result of british
artificial famines which is nothing
short of a massive
genocide
it is one of the most horrific crimes
against humanity and we are not taught
this in our education system our history
teachers will not teach you this
our history textbooks will not tell you
this and the western historians even
though they know everything will not
speak about this
shameful
aryan chaudhary says what is kemalism
why didn't mustafa kemal ataturk give
recognition to the armenian genocide and
why didn't he give independence to
kurdistan
can camalism be implemented in india
yeah so that's the question
kamal ism is
the policies is is the
entirety of the policies of mustafa
kamal atathor the great leader and the
father of the turkish republic
so mustafa kamal ataturk was the person
he was a soldier he was one of the
greatest military generals of all time
he uh
freed turkey from the
from foreign occupation from western
occupation
the turkish war of independence in the
1920s in the aftermath of the first
world war
and
it was when the bulgarians and the
greeks and everybody attacked turkey and
tried to dismember turkey and he fought
everybody off he also fought the ottoman
sultan the caliph
and he defeated everybody and he was
able to create an independent turkish
republic out of whatever was left of the
ottoman empire and the policies that he
implemented after turkey gained her
freedom
is what is known as kemalism
so there's a six point plan agenda or
something like that kim huriyet and
i forget that i forget the turkish terms
let's take a look at it okay let's let's
all go back to
our trusty wikipedia which we cannot
trust but i'm doing it just for the sake
of
saving time so let's go here let's go to
kemah
alison
so let's see what wikipedia says about
criminalization there are six with the
six point agenda the six arrows yeah
they call it the six arrows ulti
ataturkism is another synonym for
chemism so what is the philosophy
modernization philosophy which guided
the transition from the religious
ottoman empire to the unitary secular
republic of turkey the six principle
principles are
kum hirit chilik which is republicanism
hulk chilek which is populism
miliath chilek which is nationalism
is racism which means secularism
and the
chilek which means statism
and revolutionism which is including
so these are the six principles of of
chemism which are which is the uh
ideology or the methodology that mustafa
kamal atathor employed to modernize
turkey to take turkey out of the depths
of the ottoman empire and its
orthodox
way of life into the 20th century so he
transformed turkey into a modern
progressive secular
european nation from being an eastern
islamic nation
and he tried to
secularize turkey
he tried to stamp out religion and so on
and he almost succeeded
today turkey is going all the way
backwards again but
so so that that's just the cycles of
time right history is cyclic in nature
so turkey seems to be going backwards
again it's going it seems to be turning
its back on the principles of mustafa
kemal ataturk but that's what chemism is
can it be implemented in india i don't
think it needs to be implemented in
india the turks are a different kind of
people indians are a different kind of
people different temperament different
worldview different attitudes different
culture what works there doesn't mean it
is going to work here we need a
different
approach we need different solutions
solutions that are tailor-made to
india's
culture and civilization
right so it it doesn't need to be
brought into india
why didn't mustafa kemal ataturk give
recognition to the armenian genocide
so first of all he was not involved in
the army and genocide he was a soldier
at the time but he was not involved in
it
and
he saw no need to
see he was trying to build
a strong nation out of the ashes
giving recognition to the armenian
genocide would have meant that it would
have brought a great deal of shame
and a problem on to the nation that he
was trying to build and he saw no need
to burden himself with this additional
burden and that's why he don't do
anything about that why didn't he give
independence to kurdistan because he
needed the territory
he wanted to build a small compact
nation from the ruins of the ottoman
empire without giving away territory
which he could keep for himself for his
people and that's why he did not give
independence to kurdistan
right his
agenda was very clear his service was to
the people of turkey to the turkish
people
not to the kurdish people he was not
somebody
who believed in universal brotherhood
and gandhian principles and all that he
was very clear i served the people of
turkey the turkish people and the
turkish republic
now that the kurds
have a separatist agenda i am not saying
it's right or wrong or whatever
their agenda which actually is quite
justified is to have a nation for
themselves
and the homeland of the kurds the
so-called kurdistan kurdistan
is divided across the nations of turkey
and mostly turkey and iran if i'm not
mistaken
some part of it is in iraq as well and
so on
and that's why the kurds have no country
of their home of their own no homeland
of their own a majority a significant
portion of it is in anatolia present-day
turkey
and mustafa kamal atadurk was
he wanted to build a strong unified
country
and not give in to separatism and that's
why he did not give independence to
kurdistan
so these are the reasons why he did what
he did he was a dictator he was a brutal
dictator
he employed all means at his disposal to
build a strong turkey
some of the things he did can be
considered today as
massacres or crimes against humanity etc
he did what he did
he did what he had to do in his opinion
to serve his people and his country in
the long run long-term national interest
the long-term security and prosperity of
the nation and its people and the people
he had chosen to serve were the turkish
people
and that's why he did what he did there
is no right or wrong it's just history
learn history understand how things work
understand how the world
works so that's about criminalism i have
a whole lot of other questions but i
don't think i have the time to answer
them all today so i am going to stop
here now let me take a look at the
comments if you have something to say
if you have any maybe a couple of
questions here
maybe i'll answer a couple of questions
and then we will wrap it up for today
okay let me see do we have any
interesting questions something i
haven't taken up before
let me see let me see if you have
questions ask me now hi somebody say
someone is saying hi
hi hello how are you
okay my views about adolf hitler
adolf hitler lost
as a leader you must never lose if you
lose
you expose yourself and your people
to all kinds of problems
so hitler
first of all he was a loser
he lost
he could not achieve his objectives and
secondly he was a monster
he was a monster he
perpetrated the genocide of the
jewish people i don't know how many
people four to six million jews he
killed
at least a million
romani people indian origin gypsies of
europe he killed them too so i have
absolutely no sympathy
for somebody like him he was a monster
and whatever he said about him today he
deserves all of it that's all i can say
about mr
adolf hitler
okay something else let me take one more
question
anirudh says what do you think about the
future of india i think the future is
bright if the leader is right
that's what i think about the future of
india
okay i think that's it for today so
thank you everybody guys girls ladies
gentlemen friends
countrymen country women and everybody
around the world thank you so much for
watching
thank you so much for your viewership i
appreciate it more than you can imagine
thank you very much
this is it for tonight but i will see
you tomorrow in a live chat session
until then thank you very much for
watching take care
bye